MARTIN (narrating):
Let me start with a question:
How can we overcome elitism in music?
Well, let me show you one way that doesn’t work.
In September 2020,
...a Vox podcast called ‘Switched on Pop’
...released an episode about Beethoven’s 5th symphony.
To promote the podcast,
...the hosts also wrote an introductory article titled:
Here’s the thesis put forward in that article:
Before Beethoven, people clapped during performances.
Then Beethoven’s 5th symphony was premiered,
...which the authors claim required a
...‘new kind of listening’
...because it is a multi-movement work.
They then conclude that it's specifically
...this 'new kind of listening’
...that caused audiences to refrain
from clapping between movements,
...which in turn gave rise to an elitist
and exclusionary ‘polite society’
Now, apart from being a chronology drawn in crayon,
...this smoking gun presented in the article is
...oddly absent from the podcast itself,
...which really pulls its punches on
just about every aspect of this idea.
It turns out they don’t blame the 5th symphony
...or Beethoven for elitism at all.
The only connection they draw to Beethoven is that
...he’s generally revered by
people in the classical world,
...and the classical world is full of snobs.
Later, they even say:
Er, okay.
Well, wouldn’t a better title be something like:
...then?
[chuckles] What's with this image?
“Ssshhhhhh!”
This article is a weird example
of how to promote a podcast.
Put forward an eye-catching claim to get attention
...by trolling gullible classical music
listeners and sparking outrage,
...but then furiously backpedal back on that claim later
...because you know it doesn’t make any sense.
And spark outrage they did,
...probably more than they bargained for, actually,
...leaving us with this wonderful, um…
'debate':
Oh, God!
So this is the kind of
...'discourse' you get
...when you create sensationalised,
incoherent and poorly researched nonsense.
Lots of angry shouting about basically nothing.
And there has been a lot of valuable stuff
...written about elitism in
classical music over the years,
...some of which we’re going to look at later.
'Switched on Pop' could have drawn from this well,
...but chose not to.
During this debate,
...I did not see the topic of elitism discussed
...in any meaningful way,
...and this just isn’t good enough.
If you are a journalist or
a figure with a following,
...trying to make a serious comment on music,
...I think you have a duty to properly
research what you're talking about
...to seek to be as informative as possible
...in a way that doesn’t
deliberately generate antagonism.
That way, you could actually
win some hearts and minds,
...producing a net positive effect.
Elitism and exclusion are real
problems that need to be addressed,
...but antagonism won't get us there.
All that does is force the
people on the receiving end
...into a defensive crouch.
It’s lazy,
...and worse,
...it’s easy.
And, I mean,
...even if you wanted to paint
Beethoven as an unreformed elitist,
...you could at least do it with style!
There’s loads of ammunition available.
The guy was a half-mad emotional wreck.
He said all kinds of stuff:
Beethoven, 1798.
Yeah, that looks like a smoking gun, doesn’t it?
But if you were going to do it justice,
...you’d need to discuss that quote
in the right historical context,
...including the French Revolution.
You would need to paint an accurate
picture of Beethoven’s character flaws
...and put it in that in historical context too.
You would need to do work.
People aren’t simple.
Culture isn’t a straight line.
This quote is pretty useless without context.
And that leads me to the topic of this video:
elitism, which is fascinating
...because it is so sprawling and complicated,
...and more fundamental to music
than I think many people realise.
It’s, of course, a core component
of any discussion about wealth,
...which can directly affect our musical tastes.
It can refer to barriers that
prevent people studying music
...and also barriers that dissuade listeners.
Two very different cases.
It's also caught up with many forms of stereotyping,
...and above all, is utterly entangled with identity
...and woven into the fabric of class division.
But it’s also awkwardly entangled
with things that we admire:
perfection,
...sophistication,
...genius.
Even more awkwardly,
...the idea of becoming a member
of an elite is, for some,
...clearly aspirational.
And because of this contradiction,
...accusations of elitism in music occur constantly,
...and perhaps a bit too liberally.
Because if you throw the term ‘elitist’ at someone,
...it has a cluster-bomb effect
...that torches their legitimacy
in the eyes of others.
A shortcut that removes the need
to be fair or empathetic.
Perfect for a hot take.
The purpose of this video is to not do that.
It’s to look at elitism in music
...from multiple different angles and perspectives.
And this problem of not being able to
simply define elitism as one thing
...has very much affected the form of this video,
...which is going to be made up of chapters,
...each one looking at elitism
from a very different angle,
...to try and untangle it
...so that we can be more appreciative and fair,
...and also to have fun,
...because elitism is sometimes
...actually quite funny.
There are not many narrative
straight lines in this video.
No single answer.
It’s the opposite of a hot take.
It’s, uh... It’s a:
And in the end, what I hope to achieve is
...a better kind of understanding...
...for a better kind of person!
Cheers!
♪♪
Now, if we're going to talk about elitism in music,
...there’s only one place you’d start.
That’s right.
Ancient China, 5,000 years ago.
China’s most celebrated philosopher, Confucius,
...had a lot to say about the role that
music should play in shaping society.
He was informed in large part by the ‘5 classic texts’
...which tell us stories from Chinese legend.
One tendency of these legends
...is to attribute great
musical discoveries to emperors.
For example,
...music was "invented" around 2,953 B.C.
...by the Emperor Fu Xi,
...beginning with his design of the guqin,
...a string instrument comparable to the lute.
Later, around 2697 B.C.,
...another emperor, Huangdi,
...created the first Chinese scale.
He did this by sending one of
his ministers on a mission
...to locate a perfectly proportioned piece of bamboo,
...which was eventually found in the Kunlun Mountains.
And this piece of bamboo
...was then fashioned into a pitch-pipe
...that produced a fundamental tone,
...from which the first Chinese scale was derived.
So right away,
...a link is established between
the fundamental nature of music
...and the wisdom of those
rulers who discovered it
...and then shared it with their subjects.
And there are loads of stories like this.
Confucius relates another incident
...where the goddess Sunü
...was performing for the Emperor Huangdi
...on a 50-stringed instrument called the 'se'.
It seems that the resulting
music was so deeply sad
...and affected the emperor so profoundly,
...that he ordered the number
of strings reduced by half,
...because that would cut the sadness down by half.
Um…
That’s not really how music works, Huangdi.
It’s a bit like saying,
"Hey, that book’s too sad."
"Delete half the alphabet."
I mean…
Oh yes, I don’t mean to tell you your business.
I know you invented the scale and all.
Now, if we’re to believe the ancient texts,
(and given everything we’ve heard so far,)
(...why would we have reason to doubt?),
...this was not an isolated incident.
Emperors were forever taking a hand
in the music of their subjects.
But why?
Well, if we look at one of the 5 ancient texts,
...the 'Liji', we can see that
...there was an enormous spiritual
importance placed on music,
...and specifically on musical intervals.
If we take the perfect 5th for example:
...this was considered the
most special interval of all
...because its tones correspond
to the ratio of 3:2.
So music was not just a
source of aesthetic enjoyment,
...but a crucial tool that helped mankind
...appreciate and preserve cosmic balance.
Building on this idea,
...it came to be believed
...that the five notes of the scale
needed to be tuned perfectly
...in order to maintain social balance:
It actually goes much further than this.
Each individual tone was considered
to have a unique significance
...for a specific aspect of society.
I’ve put a link in the description
to a paper on this topic
...for anyone who wants to learn more.
Anyway, it was for this reason
that Confucius considered music
...to be a higher discipline than governance or law
...because he believed it had
a more fundamental impact
...on moral and social balance.
Moreover, he argued
...that anyone who aspired
to a high ranking position
...should have a sophisticated musical training,
...which would enable them to censor musical output
...and thereby safeguard the
moral character of the population.
And in making his case,
...Confucius references another
ancient text, called the 'Shu King',
...which tells a story about
another emperor called Shun.
The story goes that in order
to maintain social balance,
...Shun would tour the villages of China every year
...to test how they tuned their
instruments, which he believed
...would reveal to him the
precise nature of their problems.
And based on this,
...he’d prescribe remedies to balance
their social and economic health.
“This tuning is defective,"
"...which tells me your village is too big."
"Please dispose of all children
aged between 12 and 16."
"Thank you!”
[whoosh]
[screams and hacking noises]
[approval ding]
So, to summarise,
...a core component of the Confucian tradition
...is that the people of ancient China
...needed the musical oversight of their rulers
...because, according to Confucius,
...there was only one way music
should be written and performed.
The right way.
♪♪
In a uniquely awful book called
‘The Secret Power of Music’,
...the author David Tame makes the case
...that the music of today has led us to degeneracy,
...and that in order to regain spiritual balance,
...we must return to the musical ideas of Confucius.
It’s a real roller-coaster ride
...that takes you from one flabbergastingly
ignorant assertion to the next:
Yeah, everyone was just coasting
during that 20th century.
There’s another part in the book that I love
...where David suggests
...that if 7 horn players got together
...and played in unison,
...they would be capable of
producing a sound so powerful
...that it could reduce fortified
stone walls to rubble.
[chuckles]
Why does he think this?
Because
...that’s what the Bible
says happened at Jericho.
He goes on then to scold science
...for not being advanced
enough to prove him right.
It’s brilliant!
Book of the month!
Well, it would be book of the month
...if it weren’t for a number
of comments strewn throughout
...that are blatantly sexist,
homophobic or racist.
I’m not going to give examples here.
For the curious, I’ve put a link in the description.
(But, y'know, don’t bother)
Anyway, this whole package is a
strange appeal for spirituality
...and really puts the:
...in:
Sorry.
But there are three things in
particular about this book
...that I do find interesting.
The first is how strongly David believes
...in the rightness of Confucius’s
attitude towards music,
...that there is a spiritually
correct way to compose.
But we really don’t know
...what music from that era sounded like,
...since, for one thing,
...Confucius lived 500 years before Christ.
Not to mention, the occurrence in 212 BC
...of a catastrophe referred to as
...‘the burning of the books’,
...which was exactly as bad for
musical historians as it sounds.
The second thing I find interesting
...is how David conflates
this music he has never heard
...with the tradition of Western classical music,
...which he also thinks is spiritually correct.
Remember this point, because it's
gonna come up again in this video.
Third: in order to drive home his argument
...that the 20th century has utterly lost its way,
...David gives an example of a band that, for him,
...symbolises the total degeneracy of our age.
Can you guess who it is?
That’s right,
...it’s none other than
...the Sex Pistols?
Seriously?
The Sex Pistols? That’s the
worst thing you could think of?
Oh, no!
The working class!
Oooooooooooooh!
PRIEST:
"When punk rock groups like the Clash"
"...or the Sex Pistols perform,"
"...the hundreds of unemployed young people"
"...who go to their concerts
and listen to their songs"
"...know that those songs"
"...are the story of their lives."
MARTIN (narrating):
John Lydon, a.k.a. Jonny Rotten,
...lead singer of the Sex Pistols,
...once said in an interview that:
This sentiment has been repeated
by the band consistently,
...that their music was a means of
asserting their identities,
...unfiltered,
...in response to what they
considered to be a hostile culture
...that regularly made them feel worthless.
For example,
...in the documentary 'The Filth and the Fury',
...John describes his
experience of early education:
JOHN:
“I questioned everything.
I always have done."
"We were doing Shakespeare."
"A teacher would give me a hard time"
"...and he wouldn’t tell me
what I wanted to know."
"I’d ask outright questions,"
"...and you’re not supposed to do that."
"You’re just supposed to accept."
"It’s Shakespeare. It’s great. You’re not.”
And with this in mind,
...it’s fascinating to think
that only a few years later,
...just as the Sex Pistols were breaking through,
...a similarly unfavourable
comparison to ‘high culture’
...was thrown at him by the interviewer
Bill Grundy on live television.
BILL:
"Punk rockers."
"The new craze, they tell me."
MARTIN (narrating):
Now, for anyone who isn’t familiar with this
...train wreck of an interview,
...it’s well worth watching.
It’s also really hard to
make out what anyone is saying,
...but let me give it to you raw first:
GLEN: What?
BILL: Are you serious, or are you just making-
BILL: ...trying to make me laugh?
GLEN: Yeah.
BILL: You are serious?
GLEN: Mmm.
Bill: Beethoven,
...Mozart,
BILL: ...Bach, Brahms…
JOHNNY: They’re all heroes of ours ain’t they?
[?]
BILL: Really? [?]
JOHNNY: They’re wonderful people!
BILL: Are they?
JOHNNY: Oh, yes.
They really turn us on.
BILL: Suppose they turn other people on?
JOHNNY: Well, that’s just their tough shit.
BILL: It’s what?
Now, if you want to catch that again,
...here’s a more coherent dramatisation:
BILL: I want to know one thing.
GLEN: What?
BILL: Are you serious,
...or are you just making me-
...trying to make me laugh?
BILL: Beethoven, Mozart,
...Bach, and Brahms have all died...
MARTIN (narrating):
So, this is Bill’s shorthand for sophistication:
Beethoven, Mozart, Bach, Brahms, et cetera.
And is there any wonder,
...given John’s previous experience
of exactly this kind of comparison,
...that he reacted the way he did?
BILL: [?]
JOHNNY: They’re wonderful people!
BILL: Are they?
JOHNNY: Yes, they really turn us on!
MARTIN (narrating):
Later, when asked why he
goaded the group in this way,
...Grundy explained that his actions were:
And no doubt, there was serious antagonism
...coming from the band’s side too.
I mean, did you spot the armband
...one of the entourage is wearing?
[sighs] There’s a whole story behind that too,
...but I won’t go into it now.
There’s also Steve Jones’s
famous cursing at the end.
BILL: Go on, you have another five seconds.
BILL: Say something outrageous.
STEVE: You dirty bastard.
MARTIN (narrating):
Oh, you’ve just gotta watch it!
BILL: I’ll be seeing you soon.
I hope I’m not seeing you again.
MARTIN (narrating):
Anyway, that aside,
...from a class point of view,
...this is such a divisive interview
...because there was a lot of
media attention paid to it
...and it clearly motivated people to take sides.
BRIAN: Punk rock has become
...almost a battle cry in British society.
For many people,
...it’s a greater threat to our way of life than
...Russian communism or hyperinflation,
...and it certainly generates
more popular excitement
...than either of those.
Can I now turn to
...Bernard Brooke-Partridge in London?
BROOKE-PARTRIDGE: I think most of these groups
...would be vastly improved by sudden death.
The worst currently are the Sex Pistols
...and they are the antithesis of human kind.
MARTIN (narrating):
And what I find sad about all of this antagonism
...is how Bill is using historical figures in music
...to try and put a working class kid in his place.
It’s such a misuse of Mozart’s name.
And John’s dismissal of Mozart,
...although absolutely appropriate for the moment,
...also strikes me as kind of sad too.
It just feels like resentment
trumped empathy on both sides here,
...and the nuances of history
were discarded in favour of
...unquestioned adoration on the one side
...or total dismissal on the other.
And I can’t help but wonder
if, in a different world,
...where people didn’t invoke
Mozart’s name as if it was
...the musical equivalent of a Rolex watch,
...John could possibly find
something admirable about him.
Towards the end of 1790,
...a year before his death at the age of 35,
...Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart had reached
...a point of complete despair.
He had spent the last four years
...doing everything in his power
to attain a steady income.
His family were living well beyond their means,
...and his financial situation
was becoming increasingly worse
...due to a lack of commissions
...and a falling out of favour in Vienna.
To make matters worse,
...his wife was extremely ill,
...and after being disinherited by his father
...and estranged from his sister,
...he had no family to turn to.
His letters during this period are filled with
...anguish and terror at
what the future might hold,
...and as a last resort, he
began begging from his friends:
For a man with the stature that Mozart has today,
...it can come as a shock when you first learn about
...the incredibly unstable financial situation
...that marred the final years of his life,
...and most likely contributed to his early death.
But what is particularly
telling about his misfortune
...is that it came about directly as a result of
...his rejection of the systems
controlled by the ruling classes
...and his insistence on artistic freedom.
Freedom that may have immortalised
him as a composer today,
...but in his own lifetime,
...led to his financial ruin.
A life that ended in misery.
To understand why, we need to consider
...what the social standing of a
composer was during this period.
Mozart may have been a famous child prodigy
...whose family toured the courts of Europe,
...but they were received as
merely travelling performers,
...albeit very talented ones,
...who lived off the invitations
and gifts of the nobility.
The Empress Maria Theresa
...referred to the Mozarts as:
...and advised her son Archduke Ferdinand
...not to employ the then-teenage Mozart because:
However, despite these kinds of attitudes,
...gaining a position at court
was crucial for Mozart
...if he wished to be a professional composer.
The influential sociologist Norbert Elias
...has a great book about Mozart
that specifically covers this topic:
Composers had a middle-ranking status at court
...that was comparable to
pastry chefs, cooks and valets.
It would be better to consider
a composer from these times
...as being closer to a craftsperson
...who created works that fitted the
aesthetic requirements of those in power.
And just like a craftsperson,
...if a composer travelled too
far beyond current fashions,
...they risked losing the favour
of court, and consequently,
...any chance of a career as a composer.
And what is incredibly important to understand here
...is that the options available to composers today
...largely did not exist then.
The ruling class were the government,
...although thankfully not for very much longer.
In 1777,
...Mozart resigned his position at the
court of the Archbishop of Salzburg
...due to multiple frustrations.
Apart from having to limit his output
...to suit the tastes and conventions of court,
...he was underpaid and generally
dragged around the country
...to perform at the Archbishop’s
whim, like a servant.
In a letter to his father, Mozart recounts how,
...when he insisted on being
released from his position,
...the Archbishop’s steward
dragged him out of the building
...and literally kicked him
on his way out the door.
It didn’t matter that Mozart had performed
...at the most prestigious
courts all over the world.
It didn’t matter that Marie Antoinette
...had once doted on him when he was a child.
His standing as one of the most
revered musicians in the world
...couldn’t change the social fact
...that in the court hierarchy,
...he was still simply a musician.
Mozart’s experience as a young man
...of travelling all over Europe in
search of a position at another court
...was almost uniformly negative.
After one unsuccessful encounter in Paris,
...he wrote to his father:
And so after years of being treated in this way,
...Mozart, who was both highly
confident of his skills
...and aware that his musical
reputation was second to none,
...took the incredibly brave, and
at that time unheard of, decision
...to go out on his own and
become a freelance artist,
...relying on his own connections,
reputation and organisational ability
...to provide an income for his family
...while finally being able to
follow his own muse as a composer.
Rather than being a musical byproduct of a system
...dominated by a decaying ruling class,
...Mozart broke away in an attempt to be
...exactly the kind of composer that we revere today:
individual, visionary, and non-conforming.
However, it wasn’t quite so easy
to simply ‘break away’ completely.
Concerts were still largely an aristocratic affair
...and were invitation-only.
Yet, despite these difficulties,
...for a time,
...Mozart was very successful at
securing commissions and patronage.
But as fashions changed
...and foreign wars drained the Austrian coffers,
...he fell out of favour,
...and commissions began to go
instead to more compliant composers.
It is possible that had Mozart not died at 35,
...he may have dug himself out
of this financial predicament.
He made this leap into the unknown
...in direct opposition to the
kinds of domination and control
...that the aristocracy assumed was theirs by right.
It is quite different to the rebelliousness
demonstrated by the Sex Pistols,
...but it is similar in some way,
...in that Mozart wanted to break free of social bonds
...that both limited his art form
...and disrespected him as a composer,
...and he took on enormous risk by doing so.
A risk that has benefitted us
...a lot more than it materially
benefited him in his own lifetime.
On the topic of elitism,
...I often think that we in the West
...are caught in a bit of a daydream.
And it often seems that we think
...that the problem of elitism happens on the fringes,
...and all that we need to do is call it out
...for it to be eliminated.
The favourite whipping boy is
...obviously classical music and its link to privilege,
(which is undoubtedly a real
problem and we’ll get to that)
...but musical elitism,
...the belief that there are superior people
...who naturally occupy a premier
status above everyone else,
...is the dominant social reality
of nearly every musical genre.
We just don’t notice it,
...because it’s been like this our entire lives.
Let’s start by looking at the incredibly high status
...that we in the West confer
upon the role of the artist,
...whose fierce independence and refusal
to cater to the tastes of the public
...is celebrated.
Historically, this is a relatively recent phenomenon.
In older cultures,
...music was often seen as something that served
...a specific practical function.
We saw this a moment ago when
looking at Mozart’s period in Vienna,
...where music was most commonly
written for banquets and dancing halls.
Even the most skilled and revered composers,
...who were allowed the most freedom,
...had to operate within the tastes
of the court that they served in,
...to project the magnificence
and fashionability of that court.
As Norbert Elias writes of this period:
Today,
...we celebrate the inversion of this relationship.
The artist’s independence is revered
...and their boundary-breaking is seen as
...forward-looking and evolutionary,
...something that leads the way for
regular listeners to catch up to.
The idea of artists who write music to
cater to the wants of their audience
...is routinely looked down upon as
...‘safe’ or ‘commercial’.
And because of this,
...the more successful the songwriter or composer,
...the more they’re treated like gods
...and the more their stories are mythologised.
And this isn’t hard to spot.
It’s a fundamental component of most music marketing
...and a mainstay of music journalism.
Note the ludicrous mythology
built up around Bob Dylan
...by the likes of Rolling Stone magazine.
I like Bob Dylan.
He’s got some really nice music,
...but like all musicians, he has many flaws.
But in the 90’s, the early 2000’s,
...and even still today,
...you wouldn’t know it.
[sighs] Give me a break!
There’s a movie about him called
‘Masked and Anonymous’,
...which is one of the most insufferably
obsequious odes you’ll ever see.
It's meant to be about a fictional
character who's based on Bob Dylan
...but it's set to the actual
music of Bob Dylan and, even worse,
...stars Bob Dylan.
Yeah, that's right.
He’s playing a fictional character
that is celebrating himself.
And celebrities seem to be tripping
over themselves to be in this movie.
He must be so confused by the never-ending adoration
...that I can’t imagine he’s able to
distinguish dream from reality anymore.
Apart from that,
...it’s hard to watch the super
famous musicians of this era
...take to the stage in front of rapturous crowds
...and think ‘yes, this is a flat hierarchy’.
We’re forever informed about
...the awards ceremonies and soirees
that the musical stars attend
...with the rest of the rich and famous.
And the entire industry is
obsessed with literal rankings
...to see who is the most elite.
The Billboard 100.
The top 10.
Greatest rock musicians of all time.
Greatest pop songs of all time.
Greatest singers of all time.
Greatest guitarists of all time.
Gold records.
Platinum records.
MTV awards.
Brit awards.
Do you have what it takes to
be America’s next pop idol?
Only one may win.
The one who is the best one.
Grammy awards.
Record of the year.
Album of the year.
Song of the year.
Best new artist.
Taylor, I’mma let you finish,
...but Beyonce had one of
the best videos of all time.
Of all time!
Do I need to mention the throwing-money thing?
Or the conspicuous-consumption thing?
Or the giant-corporation-that-directs-our-kids-
...to-form-an-obsession-with-princesses thing?
Now, I’m by no means describing all music,
...but I’m certainly describing a very noticeable,
...widespread and mainstream part of it.
The presentation of musical artists
...as perfect, ethereal beings
...never ceases.
Their success and material wealth
...is often directly associated with their music.
Taylor, I'mma let you finish, but…
...what’s with you?
Forever swimming in diamonds.
Projecting images of yourself
living in luxury with your ideal...
...men's-fashion-department-store-wallpaper husband
...and your… car.
Look at that rich, rich car.
I don’t know much about cars, but man…
...THAT’s a car.
And it didn’t get here by accident, by the way.
There’s a public relations
firm who saw an opportunity
...to have this car placed in this video.
But why?
Why would they do this?
Why are cars and mansions
...and beauty and perfection
...so prominently associated with musical talent?
Well,
...there’s only one answer I
can think of that makes sense,
...and it’s not nice to face.
Because success and status are marketable.
It taps into something powerful within us.
Something that we dare not admit
...but are clearly drawn to in
some horrible, horrible way.
Because it represents our own aspirations
...to make it to the top.
To be the most beautiful.
To win the awards.
To own the car.
To be the person on the altar.
We can’t keep away from this aspiration,
...and to some extent,
(especially when we’re younger)
...these people represent our dreams.
We read the 'Top 100 Guitarists
of All Time' article and-
Oh, for Christ’s sake!
We all want to be successful
...and we all want to be the best,
...but we know that these wants are destructive
...and lead to unfairness and resentment.
So, we hate elitism,
...because it naturally forces social divisions.
We don’t want there to be a privileged hierarchy,
...we recognise that the idea is grossly unfair.
But despite that,
...if we’re to judge ourselves on a macro scale,
...as the English-speaking West,
...we permit musical elitism
...not just to exist on the fringes,
...but to thrive in the mainstream.
I think it’s safe to say that
...classical music has an image problem,
...one that greatly hampers its
ability to attract new audiences.
There are many contributing factors to this:
privilege,
...social identity,
...historical legacy,
...and also a broadly negative
perception in wider popular culture.
Let’s start with privilege,
...focusing on the U.K.
In 2012,
...the columnist Andrew Mellor wrote that
...although there has been an
effort among U.K. concert halls
...to be more welcoming and inclusive,
(for example, at the Proms)
...that it doesn’t take long for
some aspect of the classical world
...to undermine that effort:
Now, in order to address this,
...let's look at a few statistics
on education provision.
Around 92% of children in the U.K.
...study in state schools,
which don't charge fees,
...and around 7% of children
...study in fee-paying private schools.
The average university enrolment in England
...looks like this:
90% are from state schools,
...10% are privately educated.
However, if you narrow in on classical music,
...the picture is wildly different.
For example, in 2017,
...at the Royal Academy of Music in London,
...state-school-educated students
...made up only 48% of the total.
That’s the worst disparity in the country,
...far worse than both Cambridge and Oxford.
The Royal College of Music, another conservatoire,
...only did a little better at 56%.
Now, for both those conservatoires,
...those statistics are actually
quite an improvement on previous years,
...and a good sign that they are
attempting to address this imbalance.
However, their efforts are being undermined
...at the primary education level.
A report by the British Phonographic
Industry in 2019 found that:
So, right away, we can see how in the U.K.,
...the more affluent your parents are,
...the more opportunities you’ll have to study music.
This produces a pretty fundamental problem:
many instruments are often just too costly and expensive.
So if a school has no free provision,
...children of low-income families who study there
...will have no opportunities at all,
...whereas those from wealthier backgrounds
...will at least have the option
of hiring a private tutor.
In addition,
...since classical music is a very
financially precarious profession,
...parents earning low incomes are far less likely
...to encourage their children to pursue it
...in favour of more stable professions.
Apart from the lack of opportunities
for low-income families,
...there’s also the issue of
under-representation of ethnic minorities
...and massive under-representation
of those with long-term disabilities.
Income can play a part here too,
...but there are many more
factors to take into account.
And I could only do them justice by
discussing them in separate videos.
For now, I’ve put a few links in the description
...to reports that go into much more detail.
It is worth mentioning that there
are those fighting back in the U.K.
...to help children from disadvantaged communities
...gain access to instruments and music lessons,
...such as the 'In Harmony' programme,
...which is supported by the Arts Council
and Department of Education.
I’ve provided a link to a
report about that programme too.
But despite bright spots
like the ‘In Harmony’ programme,
...the general decrease of
provision in state education
...is gradually pricing out poorer communities.
This perversely forces classical music to be
...something that only the more privileged can study,
...perpetuating and even hardening the class divide.
In the book 'Class, Control, and Classical Music',
...the author Anna Bull notes that:
But this is only one side of the coin.
On the other side is the
...cancerous image problem that classical music has,
...which can be clearly seen by looking
at its place in popular culture:
in advertising,
...branding,
...television,
...movies,
...broadcasting,
...everywhere.
Where do I even begin?
Let’s look at the popular HBO show 'Succession',
...which is about an extraordinarily wealthy
...but also highly dysfunctional family
...who sit at the head of a global news empire.
Think the Murdochs.
The show features a small cast of characters,
...who spend their time cynically
manoeuvring and backstabbing
...in an attempt to succeed their aging father,
...who is himself
...one of the most unlikable characters in TV history.
And throughout the show,
...as these characters travel around
...from one ridiculously opulent setting to the next,
...this is their soundtrack:
It’s the same story with the movie
'House of Gucci',
...also about a fabulously wealthy
...but highly dysfunctional family.
The reason this music is effective
...is because in both TV and cinema,
...music in the Classical or late-Baroque style
...has become a globally understood shorthand
...for wealth, opulence and privilege.
On the screen in general,
...classical music has become reified to the point
...where it just means ‘elitism’.
So even if we solved the first half of the problem,
(providing equal opportunities to study the art form)
...its image problem is unlikely
to go away anytime soon.
Advertisers often use classical music
...to help position their products in the premium space:
And then there’s this entire genre of car commercials,
...that fetishise the concept
of ‘engineering precision’
...by linking it to classical music.
One of the worst offenders here is Alfa Romeo:
...but the kings of this genre are Hyundai:
To dwell in the world of advertising for a moment,
...let's look at this ad for cognac
...and its use of the classical composer cliché:
YARON: This project
...was born around a challenge.
To try to translate into sound
...the magic
...of one note.
[glasses clinking]
MARTIN (narrating):
Ah, it’s just so sophisticated.
And then we watch
...as this composer applies his
genius to this musical challenge,
...following his impulses,
...pursuing his muse,
...free (I’m sure) from any external influence.
YARON: How can a little drop
...of Louis XIII
...resonate?
MARTIN (narrating):
Ah, Louis treize!
L’enfer, c’est les autres.
B- B- By-
By the way, you know a regular bottle of this stuff
...costs around £3000?
"The brandy,"
"...beloved by everyone"
"...from Napoleon"
"...to Jay-Z."
Hold on. How do we know Jay-Z drinks this stuff?
[laughs]
It's- It’s Louis TREIZE,
...uh, Jay-Z!
Oh God, this use of French pronunciation
in English-speaking commercials.
Advertising really is the closest vantage point
...from which we can peer into the abyss.
In the language of cinema,
...classical music is also sometimes used
...as an indication that a character is repressed.
For example, in the Hangover Part II,
...let’s look at the story arc
for this repressed character,
...which feels like it was
written on the back of a napkin.
Man getting married.
Dad of bride doesn’t like man.
Dad loves son,
...who classical be.
Bach Prelude in G,
...because… Of course.
Son repressed.
Party time!
Oh no, hangover happen.
Where son?
Search for son.
Son found!
Oh, no.
Son lose finger.
He no longer cello classical be.
But son not sad ‘cause liberated.
Hangover un-elitied him.
He happy normal now.
Take that, daddio!
[Credits with Martin doing Mozart impression]
[Also, don’t get me started about Hannibal Lecter]
'Britain’s Got Talent' have this
gimmick they pull fairly regularly,
...where a character comes out on stage
...and then begins performing on a boring old instrument,
...like a flute.
Everyone yawns.
So boring.
Simon Cowell wants to impress upon your children
...that this is boring.
Aww, hold on!
He’s playing a crutch!
Awesome!
Now it’s good!
In Ireland, if you’re a student going to a party
...and you want to have a drink,
...but you’re super low on funds,
...the famous option of last
resort is a bottle of vodka
...sold by the German discount supermarket
'Lidl', or possibly ‘Leedle’,
...it’s a national debate how you pronounce it.
Anyway. all you’ll need is €10
...and a cast-iron stomach,
...because this stuff will test you beyond
...whatever you think your limits are,
What’s it called?
'Rachmaninoff'.
Why?
Because wine and spirit brands
...never intentionally look cheap,
...so the low end of the market needs
to double down on their brand identity
...to create the illusion of quality.
This then reassures the
alcohol-obsessed undergrads of Ireland
...that their choice isn’t utterly appalling.
But this stuff is about as far from
classy as you’re likely to get!
It tastes like you’re drinking leakage
...from Rachmaninoff’s decomposing corpse!
It’s not just misrepresentation from the outside
...that affects the perception of classical music.
The enemy is most certainly also within,
...because the problem with all this coding
of classical music as an elite artform
...is that it appeals to some people.
Some people like to think
of themselves as classy folk.
I mean, I could give loads of examples,
...but that would just delay
the moment until I mention
...André Rieu.
I cannot really wrap my head around this man.
His concerts are so odd.
It's mainly just a bunch of short fragments
...of the most clichéd pieces
from the classical repertoire.
If he’s doing Beethoven 9, for example.
...he won’t play the full thing.
Not even a single movement.
Although, I guess if there are no movements,
...then people can’t not clap.
So I don’t know, perhaps he’s onto something.
But anyway,
...all you get are these dull fragments
...of the most famous bit
from, say, the 'Ode to Joy',
...and then on to another cliched fragment
...from some another well known work.
But there’s a bizarre contradiction here.
On the one hand,
...this is clearly an attempt
to make classical music
...quote ‘accessible’ unquote,
...but on the other hand,
...look at the stage setup which is, like,
...Disney-level aristocratic.
I find this so strange.
He's ditched all the complexity,
...but kept all the trappings of wealth?
Literally selling that cheesy
illusion of classical music
...that exists in popular culture?
And I honestly cannot understand
what audiences get out of this.
I- I guess it’s just fun?
Dressing up in your Sunday best
...to go see the magical man who lives in a castle?
I’m not even joking about that, by the way.
On the homepage of his website, it says:
I mean...
I-
Urgh.
Whatever.
And here’s a thought experiment.
Imagine a young person chancing upon this on TV.
With no prior experience,
...they’d be forgiven for concluding that
...this is what ‘classical music’ is:
‘distant’,
‘unreachable’,
‘old, white and rich’,
‘alien’,
'musically boring',
...and 'just awful'.
While what’s actually going on is that
...Andre is selling the image of elitism
...to non-classical audiences
...while ditching the musical substance
and essence of classical music.
It’s bourgeois cosplay.
For those invested in trying
to diversify classical music
...and modernise its image,
...this is an internal act of cultural terrorism!
The last thing I want to talk about
that really hurts the classical genre
...is the widespread perception that
it is the music of the middle class.
Now, as we’ve seen earlier,
...this is factually true,
...but it doesn’t have to be a
fait accompli for all eternity.
But despite all the hard work being
done to change this situation,
...there are those audience members who are
...doing their best to uphold the status quo,
...who get way too caught up with the identity
...that they think classical music confers on them,
...I would argue, largely informed by
...the commercialisation and reification
of classical music we have looked at.
These are the folk you’ll find tutting at people
...who clap between movements.
These are the people who complain on message boards
...about the riffraff who fail to dress up.
“It’s the least you can do."
"You are listening to Mozart!”
Incidentally, if you’re going to like,
subscribe or comment on this video,
...could you please just wait
until it’s over before you do?
Y’know, show a bit of decorum,
...for Christ’s sake?
Concert halls themselves seem
strange to the uninitiated.
...almost hermetically sealed off from the
...‘outside’ world of day-to-day social concerns.
This was, of course, by design,
...so that audiences can enjoy music for music’s sake.
However, to some,
...especially those from non-white,
non-middle-class backgrounds,
...these spaces feel cold and unwelcoming.
Anna Bull likens the sonically-sealed
space of the concert hall to:
And it’s worth mentioning another statistic here.
In the U.K., people with degrees
...are six times more likely to listen
to classical music than those without.
And the point for me is not that
this is automatically a bad thing.
It’s that the association is toxic
...and leans into the cliché that
classical music is a signifier of refinement.
This is a problem because, as Anna Bull observes,
...it clashes with what she calls:
We saw this exactly in that Sex Pistols interview.
Classical music was the last thing
they wanted to be associated with.
So all this stuff together,
...the economic barriers,
...the high representation of
professional, middle-class listeners,
...the weird social codes.
...the preference for cold, formal listening spaces.
Then add to that
...the crass commercialisation and
fetishisation of classical music
...as a way of tarting up a product
...or marking a character as dislikable.
It all adds up.
And the only thing I can think of
that we can do to stop it is...
...well, this.
Talk about it.
Identify it, and then take
little steps everywhere we can
...to break these clichés,
...be more inviting and fun for others.
Do our best to describe
...why long-form, and often challenging, music
...can be rewarding and exciting.
And don't get too bothered if people don’t care.
Redesign musical education to
not be so backwards-looking.
Lay siege to André Rieu’s castle,
...drink middle-shelf spirits.
Cancel our HBO subscriptions
...as a highly obscure and
statistically indecipherable rebellion
...against their non-diegetic soundtrack choices.
And we should also take the hard road too:
showing how we’re not elitist
...by responding with warmth and empathy
...rather than hostility whenever we’re criticised.
And then,
...possibly,
...we may develop a genre that sheds
...the nasty aspects of the classical legacy
...without completely losing sight of why it is
...still a really exciting art form.
In 1958,
...a now infamous article
...appeared in a journal called ‘High Fidelity’.
It was written by the American
composer Milton Babbitt,
...who was also a music and mathematics
professor at Princeton University.
The article was titled:
...and we’ll return to that title in a moment.
But a bit of background first.
Babbitt was involved in developing
...what is now referred to as
‘integral’ or ‘total serialism’,
...which was a highly complex expansion
of the ideas of Arnold Schoenberg.
Now, it’s worth mentioning that even to his admirers,
...Babbitt’s music is hard work.
Not something you can jump straight
into and immediately enjoy.
♪♪
"Do I necessarily hear the things in Milton’s music"
"...that he would like me to hear?"
"No!"
MARTIN (narrating):
Babbitt was becoming increasingly frustrated by two things.
First, he felt that the role of composer
...was not respected enough in academia,
...which considered music to be
more of a public commodity
...than a serious form of research.
Second, Babbitt very much disliked
...the inherited concert hall tradition,
...where audiences accustomed to the more
conventional music of Beethoven or Mahler,
...and who would have no idea
what integral serialism was,
...would be completely unprepared for his music
...and would often react with open hostility to it.
And so, in his article,
...he put forward the following argument.
First, he acknowledged
...that his music was inaccessible
...and pointed out that it required musical training
...and knowledge of musical history to appreciate,
...and made the case that this
should not be considered a bad thing.
Second, he acknowledged
...that unprepared listeners could not reasonably
...be expected to like his music,
...but were not justified when
they reacted with hostility.
And his appeal was this:
my music may not be popular
in a concert hall setting,
...but it is valuable as research,
...because it seeks to advance
the boundaries of music
...by exploring sonorities and structures
...outside the common point of reference,
...unbound from the need to cater to
...the limited understanding of the casual listener.
And he points out that this state of affairs
...is generally accepted in many
other forms of academic research.
There were three kinds of responses to this.
Some hated the idea that a composer
would encourage his colleagues
...to abandon the wider listening audience
...and retreat into academia.
Some saw it as a defensive lashing-out at listeners
...for not liking his music.
More about that in a second.
Others still were irritated by
Babbitt’s positioning of his work
...as an ‘advancement’ of music at all.
Now, I have some sympathy for Milton’s position here.
In particular, I think he is right to
defend complexity and inaccessibility
...against what can sometimes be
...an overbearing insistence among audience members
...that music should do what they want it to do.
It’s a kind of ‘the customer’s always right’ attitude
...that refuses to engage with an alien point of view.
By telling someone what they should be saying,
...you’re not listening.
But, that said, there are
...two big problems with this article:
First, the name.
Now, as we’ve seen,
...the intended title was
‘The composer as specialist’.
The published title, however, was:
And as you can imagine,
...this hostile name is one of the main reasons
...why the article got as much notice as it did.
But this name was actually a change
...made by the editor of 'High Fidelity'
...without Babbitt’s consent.
The second problem is Milton’s
...not-amazingly-well-concealed bitterness.
And it’s this aspect of the
essay that makes it, for me,
...a little whinge-y in tone,
...but also actually quite funny too.
I mean, take this bit for example:
"Imagine, if you can,"
"...a layman chancing upon a lecture on"
"...'Pointwise Periodic Homeomorphisms'."
"At the conclusion,"
"...he announces, 'I didn’t like it.'"
"Social conventions being
what they are in such circles,"
"...someone might dare inquire, 'Why not?'"
"Under duress, our layman discloses"
"...precise reasons for his
failure to enjoy himself."
"He found the hall chilly,"
"...the lecturer’s voice unpleasant,"
"...and he was suffering the
digestive aftermath of a poor dinner."
"His interlocutor understandably
disqualifies these reasons"
"...as irrelevant to the content
and value of the lecture,"
"...and the development of
mathematics is left undisturbed."
STEVE: "You dirty bastard."
MARTIN (narrating):
Oh, I don’t know.
From time to time, it’s just fun to
just listen to a passionate person
...go on a bit of a tirade.
The- There’s another moment
where he points out that
...if his music didn’t exist,
...barely anyone would notice.
But rather than write this in a way
...that might appear self-reflective and honest,
...he wrote instead:
MARTIN (narrating):
Oh, no. Don’t say that!
Don’t say that if you don’t get
special funding, music will die.
STEVE: [extremely slowed-down and pitch-shifted]
"Bastard."
MARTIN (narrating):
Oh. [laughs] I'm sorry,
...I just find this article really funny.
But poor MBabb!
By his own admission, he’s now best known,
...not as a composer, but as the author of:
...which is unfortunate.
With a different title
...and a little more context and less bitterness,
...it probably would have
Passed relatively unnoticed.
‘Gatekeeping’ is a term that permeates
...the majority of disputes about music.
It’s typified by these kinds of phrases:
The reason these statements bug people is obvious.
If you find music you like,
...these kinds of comments make you feel
...your enjoyment is somehow inferior.
I don’t think this requires much expanding on.
No one likes being talked to this way.
And there’s one thing in particular I want to discuss
...that I think gets to the root of what
many people consider to be gatekeeping.
It’s what I’m going to call:
A video released last year by
the YouTuber 'Timbah.On.Toast'
...exemplifies the power of the imposter phenomenon.
It’s called:
In this video,
...he describes his experience as a teenager in London,
...just as the dubstep genre was beginning to take hold.
You should really watch it. It’s fantastic.
He describes how he first got sucked into
...the artistic, slowed-down,
ambient quality of early dubstep,
...and how he watched with joy as
it began to spread across London.
How performances were minimalistic with no bling,
...no bro-manship,
...and no pretentiousness at all.
People just turned up to shows,
...stood there and listened.
He describes how this scene was
a refuge for him and his friends,
...a community of their own that
he actively participated in.
Then he described how, as the genre evolved,
...a more punchy, dance-friendly variant began to emerge
...that eventually led to the famous
'womp-womp', 'screech' sound we all know.
He describes how DJs gradually began including
...more and more of this style in their sets
...to encourage audiences to go wild,
...and how he liked this development at first
...until he began to notice that it was taking over,
...changing the entire dynamic of shows,
...which became more and more about crazy dancing
...and less about detached listening.
And as DJs continued trying to outdo each other,
...it became an arms race that completely drowned out
...the quieter, ambient, artistic stuff.
And then he talks about Skrillex,
...who, inspired by this new strain of Dubstep,
...ramped it up to be even more blunt and harsh,
...and in doing so, reached massive commercial success.
This brought in a completely new audience
...who considered Skrillex to be a figurehead.
And so dubstep was utterly redefined,
...carrying little of the spirit of the community
...that Timbah was a part of.
And he resented this.
He felt it dispossessed him of
the scene that he grew up with.
A feeling shared by many people around the U.K.
...who remembered dubstep as something else,
...who, in their frustration,
...lashed out at U.S.' dubstep for being commercial,
...inartistic and dumb.
Many people refer to this as ‘gate-keeping’,
...but I think it goes much deeper.
I think of it more as a kind of misdirected sadness
...at the loss of one’s own community and identity.
To give one quote from a dubstep forum:
And this way of looking at things
...helps us when considering other genres.
For example, jazz,
...the genre that suffers
...from what is probably the most famous
example of the imposter phenomenon:
Kenny G.
His music is a common joke even in mass media,
...generally considered to be overly safe
...and lacking in any artistic depth,
...the choice of shopping malls around the world.
NORM: Kenny G
...has a Christmas album out this year.
Hey! Happy birthday, Jesus.
I hope you like crap!
[audience laughing]
And it’s this pervasive sense of Kenny G as
...flat, uninteresting, aeroplane food
...that made his association with
jazz so troubling for some musicians.
Because if enough people had come to think
...that jazz is the sound of Kenny G,
...and enough new musicians had piled into the genre
...to replicate Kenny G’s success,
...then jazz itself would slowly be redefined.
Its legacy and history,
...unknown to this new audience,
...would fade away.
And for some listeners or performers
...whose identities are caught up with jazz,
...that was a scary prospect,
...and many hit out to prevent it from happening.
Take the famous overreaction of
the jazz guitarist Pat Metheny,
...who took issue with Kenny G performing
...alongside footage of the late Louis Armstrong:
Metheny also spends time discussing
...whether Kenny G’s music can
even really be said to be jazz.
"And now that’s what people think jazz is."
"Well, that’s not what jazz is, at all."
And to me, that’s the real message:
Metheny wants to reinforce the history
and meaning of jazz as much as he can
...because he perceives Kenny G to be a threat to it,
...which in turn is a threat to him and his identity.
I think it’s a completely understandable fear.
Mass media can completely change perceptions
...and history can be forgotten if it isn’t passed down.
Not that that justifies Metheny’s
hyperbolic, mean-spirited delivery.
Speaking for myself, being a contemporary composer,
...I have a somewhat similar feeling
...about the music of Ludovico Einaudi,
...a man who is, in many respects,
...the Kenny G of the classical world.
Now, none of what I’m about to
say is particularly justifiable,
...so bear with me.
The only difference for me between Kenny G and Einaudi
...is that Kenny G has a sound.
With Einaudi, I can’t really detect
...any artistry or identifiable voice at all.
Even the titles of his songs
...just scream low-effort to me:
And I’m not alone.
It’s not a secret that many ‘classical music’ listeners
...have no time for Einaudi.
And I’m pretty sure that the main reason for this
...is because they see him as an imposter.
Someone who threatens,
...due to his success and mass appeal,
...to redefine the classical genre as a kind of
...non-experimental, bland, elevator music.
For me personally,
...the identity threat from
Einaudi is not exactly that.
It’s a bit different.
What I value in music is originality,
...experimentation,
...and a resistance to mass-media homogenisation,
...and Einaudi’s music is, to me,
...the purest distillation of
the opposite of those qualities.
So, I see his incredible success as a sign
...that an ever increasing number of people
...don’t care about what I care about.
This is a purely emotional reaction
based on a perspective that I have,
...which makes his music seem
so much more objectionable to me
...than it does to many other people.
As I said, I can’t really
justify it in any serious way.
But being able to justify it isn’t the point.
The point is that the imposter phenomenon is
...very emotionally understandable
...and easy to empathise with,
...and I think it’s very often the
reason why people make statements like
"I liked it before it was popular",
"I prefer the early stuff",
"The scene was great before it became commercial".
You don’t deal with these kinds of positions
...by hammering them with iron logic.
You don’t deal with them by
shouting at them on Twitter.
You deal with them
...by recognising their sense of threat.
♪♪
In 1966,
...the fate of the Chinese people
was about to take a dark turn.
Their leader, Mao Zedong,
...a man whose policies had unnecessarily
...caused the largest famine in human history,
...(doing away with) between 20-40 million people,
...was about to attempt a massive undertaking.
His plan, called
...the ‘Great Proletarian Cultural Revolution’,
...was an attempt to completely reset society.
And a large part of this plan included
...the elimination of all
historical and foreign influences,
...in particular Confucianism
...and anything from the West,
...both of which Mao considered to be
the cause of China’s historical problems.
However, his number one focus was to eliminate
...all vestiges of what he saw as 'bourgeois elitism',
...which he believed was perpetuated through education.
So, China’s education system was completely dismantled,
...with all its schools and universities shut.
Teachers, scientists,
...and anyone else considered to be a
member of the intellectual bourgeois
...were routinely beaten,
...interred,
...publicly humiliated,
...harassed into ending their own lives, or:
All music prior to the Cultural Revolution
...was considered fundamentally contaminated.
China’s indigenous traditional music was deemed
...a hopelessly old-fashioned remnant of feudal culture.
The ideas of Confucius on music were completely rejected
...and his writings outlawed.
Mao even went as far as to blow up Confucius’s tomb.
Western classical music was deemed to be
...completely contaminated
...due its history of aristocratic patronage,
...and was outlawed,
...and those who taught Western
classical music at conservatories
...were treated with incredible harshness:
SHUZHEN: Ten of our teachers died from, uh,
...from by [sic]:
...because they couldn't
...stand the humiliation and:
...especially the:
...of the mind.
MARTIN (narrating):
Official media from this period
described Beethoven as a
“German capitalist composer”,
...whose work:
...whatever that means.
Writing about the Western classical tradition,
...the then-culture-minister, Yu Huiyong wrote:
So, by dubiously linking classical
music to Confucius in this way,
...the government under Mao created
...a grand elitist conspiracy in music
...so they could position themselves as the ones
...who would finally sweep it away.
The ambition here is kind of astounding.
Mao understood that music was a
key aspect in identity formation.
He wanted to avoid a future
...where a band like the ‘Sex Pistols’ could exist.
So, since he believed that
...all music was associated with class,
...and he wanted to build a classless society,
...banning all prior music up
to that point wasn’t enough.
He had to wipe the entire history
of music out of existence too.
And you can see the logic here.
Everything I’ve described in
this video up until now has shown
...that elitism in music is completely entwined
...with history, class division and education.
So this is one way that someone has tried to answer
...the original question I posed at
the very beginning of this video,
'how do we end elitism in music'.
Mao’s answer?
Completely wipe everyone’s memory of
everything that has ever happened,
...and start from scratch.
And even this didn’t work.
Why?
Because many musicians secretly continued
...to practice traditional and
classical music behind closed doors,
...at great personal risk.
The Cultural Revolution came to an end
...with Mao’s death in 1976,
...the same year, incidentally, that
the Sex Pistols gave that interview.
His successor, Deng Xiaoping,
...reopened schools and universities,
...and those people who had been
practising classical music in secret
...now emerged to teach the next generation of musicians.
Shortly after, China began to reopen to the world.
The American violinist Isaac Stern
was invited to tour China,
...where he visited music halls
and institutions around the country,
...meeting hundreds of children
who’d perform for him along the way.
At one point,
...he raised a question about
the talents of these children,
...asking, a little clumsily,
...why the younger children aged 7 to 11
...showed so much more promise
...than the older children aged 17 and above.
ISAAC: "...the young people,"
"...8, 9, 10, 11..."
"...remarkable."
"But 17, 18, 19, 20, 21,"
"...something happened to them."
"What happened in between?"
MARTIN (narrating):
And then someone explained to him,
...those aged 17 and above didn’t study music
...because for most of their lives,
...education was illegal.
Regardless,
...Isaac’s visit caused a massive stir in China
...and was one of the events
that led to a gigantic surge
...of enthusiasm for Western classical music
...that continues to this day,
...aided in large part by the Communist party,
...who, completely reversing the position of Mao,
...have invested gigantic sums into its cultivation
...through arts funding and venue construction
...that dwarfs anything seen in the West.
And as a result of this combination of organic influence
...and massive state funding,
...China is the only place in the world
where classical music is growing,
...being practiced by an estimated 100 million people.
China has, for a while now,
...been the largest consumer and exporter of instruments,
...in particular the violin and piano.
This is an incredible cultural U-turn
that’s a little hard to explain,
...and there are certainly different
perspectives on why it has happened:
The conductor, Li Delun,
...one of the champions of the
classical revival in China, argued:
Another influence comes from Confucianism,
...which has been completely revived in China
...and embraced by the Communist Party of today,
...who, after 40 years in power,
...see less advantage in Mao’s
...‘tear everything to shreds’ revolutionary spirit
...and a lot more advantage in the Confucian emphasis
...on harmonious society and respect for authority.
And similar to Confucian thinking,
...there are those in the Communist party
...who have encouraged the widespread
adoption of Western classical music
...as a means of directing the shape that society takes.
To give one example,
...in 1994,
...the then-President, Jiang Zemin,
...conceived of music appreciation classes,
...which emphasised the value of
classical music over pop music,
...because:
But there are those in China
...who do not see these developments in such a rosy light.
Commenting on the obsession with Western classical music
...and how it is linked to the ideas of Confucius,
...the musician Wu Han said:
And what strikes me about all of this
...is how much the appreciation of music
...is impossibly entwined with a history of leadership
...that has attempted to harness it as a tool
...to mould society into a shape of their liking.
Yet, at the same time,
...you can't possibly argue that there isn’t also
...a profound love of Western
classical music mixed in there too.
Those who practised it in secret for
10 years during the Cultural Revolution
...are more than enough proof of that.
And the fact that the Cultural Revolution
itself was a complete failure
...is also proof that there is a limit to
how much the people can be brainwashed.
China and the West have more similarities
than differences when it comes to music,
...but the differences are fascinating.
China’s history of music is like
...an alternate dimension that
the West can compare itself to,
...where some ideas grew stronger there
...that failed to influence as much here.
For example, our own revered philosopher, Plato,
...made a very similar case to Confucius
...about how music should be safeguarded
...to preserve the moral character of the people.
But these were largely thrown out by Aristotle,
...who emphasised the importance of observable experience
...over unprovable concepts of
...a musical spiritual connection to the cosmos.
So today,
...the main proponents of the
Platonic-Confucian ideal of music in the West
...are largely relegated to New Age conspiracy theories,
...like the 'A=432' crowd
...or the wonderfully well researched classic
‘The Secret Power of Music’.
As I mentioned at the outset,
...the ideas discussed in this video
...are not part of one linear argument.
Each chapter has its own purpose,
...and it wouldn’t be possible to conclude them all here.
Instead, I’ll offer a final thought.
Mao’s disastrous and misguided policies on music
...were not based on musical ideas.
They were literal, social ideas,
...about things like class and self-sufficiency,
...applied to a non-literal art form.
And by doing this,
...by applying a logical framework
filled with rigid associations
...to determine the country’s musical direction,
...Mao was treating his people like a jigsaw puzzle,
...as if they could be moved around until they made sense.
He didn’t think about what music meant to them
...or whether their experiences fell outside
...the shockingly basic framework he had devised.
This is profoundly unempathetic.
He was living in the dumb, literal world of his own head
...and ignoring anything that didn’t fit in it.
And this is a mistake we can learn lessons from.
When we encounter musical ideas we think are misguided,
...we tend to fall back on literal, logical explanations
...for why people hold them.
Explanations that often take
the shape of a mental pathology.
A theory about what must be wrong with their minds
...that they’d arrive at such a flawed conclusion.
They have basic tastes.
They’re uneducated.
They’re living in the past.
They’re latching onto a trend.
They’re pretentious.
They like complexity for complexity’s sake.
They’re deluded.
They’re confused.
They’re looking for attention.
They think they’re superior.
And so on.
In the absence of an explanation,
...we fill the gaps with a story that makes sense.
Music will always present a tempting battleground
...for us to hash out our social differences,
...because it’s such an emotional and personal medium,
...one where intentions can easily be misconstrued
...or deliberately misrepresented.
Instead, what we need to do is get better at
...putting ourselves in the position
of people we don’t understand,
...and when encountering a
preference we think is preposterous,
...take the hard road
...and assume that there must be some
legitimate reason for it existing,
...one we may not be able to ever completely explain.
And the only instance where this isn’t true
...is my dismissal of André Rieu’s music,
...which is objectively terrible,
...and I know what I’m talking about
...because
...I’m brilliant.